# **Tosin Orekoya BSc CPFA**

Email: olaseni.orekoya@yahoo.co.uk

**Mobile**:07936099346

Home Address: Dagenham, London, RM9

**LinkedIn:** tosin-orekoya **GitHub:** /tosin1691

.

# **Profile**

I am a personable, engaging and experienced chartered accountant currently undergoing a career transition to the digital space. My interest in web development stems from my passion for problem solving. The feeling of a great sense of success after solving a complex problem is indescribable and I look forward to working in a field that greatly links with my passion. I am currently studying in a Frontend Web Development bootcamp certificate program at edX Online, where I am continuing to build my skills in HTML & CSS, JavaScript, React.js, and responsive web design. I thoroughly enjoy collaborating with my peers to bring our software visions to life.

# **Technical Skills**

JavaScript ES6+, CSS3, HTML5, Node.js, jQuery, tailwind, React, Responsive web design, Bootstrap and GitHub

**Education** 

Oct 2023 - Feb 2024 EdX Online

Bootcamp Certification Programme

Oct 2014 - Dec 2018 Chartered Institute of Public Finance and Accountancy

Chartered Public Finance Accountant

Oct 2010 - July 2013 University of Southampton

BSc (Hons) Accounting and Finance (2.1)

Sept 2008 - June 2010 Loreto College, Manchester

A-Level: Mathematics (A\*), Accounting (A), ICT (B)

Sept 2003 – June 2008 St Peter's RC High School, Manchester

GCSE: 12A-Cs, including Mathematics (A) and English (C)

# **Experience**

# Mar 2021 - Present Department for Transport - Financial Control Manager

- Undertaking reviews of key financial processes to identify risks and control weaknesses and embedded changes to improve the control environment; through engaging key stakeholder, resulting in savings of up to £300k.
- Acted as co-chair of the DfT Control Network Group and supporting the delivery of its key responsibilities of driving the controls agenda, assurance, risk and counter fraud activity.
- Working closely with Cabinet Office, HM Treasury and Subject Matter Experts within DfT to ensure guidance and advice on spending controls remain relevant and compliant with Managing Public Money guidance and Cabinet Office Spending Controls framework.
- Working closely with Governmental departments and key internal stakeholders to improve DfT's compliance with the Government Grants Functional Standards leading to savings of up £2.3m annually.
- Working closely with Internet Auditors to support the audit of the DfT's Grant Function and implementing and actioning recommendations on the audit report.
- Presenting to the audit committee to keep senior management and non-executive board member abreast of recent development in financial controls.
- Review off-payroll tax resulting to prevent fines, resulting in no fines from HMRC review of records and savings of up to £350k
- Led on tax French rep to recover VAT. This work resulted in £18m recovery in tax for the department
- Identified issues in opt-to-tax processes resulting in recovery of tax of £12m and awarded Local Recognition Award and nominated for the DfT rising star award as a result
- Led the design of ... Nominated for best .... At the Government Finance Function
- Line managed up to 4 people to aid their development and unlock their full potential; 2 staff members were promoted under my leadership

# **Tosin Orekoya BSc CPFA**

#### Sept 2017 - Feb 2021 Grant Thornton UK LLP - Audit Assistant Manager / Manager

- Led on audits since June 2016, for clients with gross expenditure of up to £2bn including Various NHS Bodies (Trusts, FTs & CCGs), County Councils, London Boroughs, District Councils, Universities and companies reporting under Code of Practice supported by IFRS and FRS 102
- Collaborated with senior managers and engagement leaders, overseeing multiple engagements simultaneously and using project planning tools such as gantt charts to ensure successful delivery of audit engagements
- Proactively developed and maintained professional working relationships, communicating openly with management and escalating problems/delays promptly
- Led on resource planning for multiple audit engagements bringing in up to £1.8m in revenue fees over my tenure including overseeing budget planning, financial performance analysis and profit optimisation.
- Led planning meetings, authorised and reviewed the work of junior staff whilst coaching and mentoring on site.
- Executed and reviewed test of internal controls; formed robust improvement recommendations, including material control deficiencies within the audit findings report
- Analysed complex legal documentation and large volumes of documents requiring the ability to review key issues and offer robust opinions in respect of those issues
- Spearheaded, formulated, and presented audit plans and audit findings reports for presentation to the Audit Committee of our clients
- Collaborated with senior management to identify strategic audit priorities and develop annual audit plan
- Kept abreast of changes and amendments to accounting standards, CIPFA guidance, other pronouncements, and their impact on the audit strategy
- Collaborated with engagement lead on audit tenders for new bids and presented at invitation to Pitch meetingss
- Acted as people manager to junior staff to aid their development as audit professionals, and enabled them to unlock their full potential and deliver to the highest professional standard

#### Aug 2014 - Aug 2017 Grant Thornton UK LLP - Audit Associate

- Worked in a leading Public Sector and Third Sector Assurance team providing financial statement audits, value for money reviews focusing on financial resilience and other accountancy services to local government bodies, NHS bodies, Charities, Universities and Companies in London, and the South East region
- Led several audit engagements with the responsibility of delivering efficient, effective and value-added services to our clients; and collaborated with colleagues to complete and deliver on advisory projects
- Executed assurance, independent examination and grant certification assignments for charities and public sector clients
- Studied towards my CIPFA qualification whilst juggling other work commitments

# Positions of Responsibility

#### 2015 - 2021. Grant Thornton IDEA Champion

- Spearheaded and presented IDEA training sessions for new members of staff including trainees, secondees and contactors with the aim of developing their knowledge and capabilities of using the data analysis tool
- Headed firm wide technical support on the application of IDEA during audit fieldwork
- Participated in IDEA champion workshops to update my knowledge of the software

#### 2015 - 2017 Financial Reporting Champion

- Collaborated with the firm's national quality team to update and maintain knowledge of technical auditing and accounting standards
- Provided support to more senior members of the team with technical auditing and accounting issues on behalf of our clients
- Influenced leadership in the delivery of the team's annual financial reporting training

# 2011- 2013 Captain (Southampton University ACS and Management Basketball Team)

- Scheduled and Organised weekly training sessions
- Created training drills to develop, maintain and motivate skilled players
- Demonstrated and improved leadership skills
- Delegated of roles to team members

#### **Skills and Interests**

**Languages**: Native English speaker, intermediate in Yoruba

**Sport:** Participant in recreational basketball, gym, fitness and participated in several running events **Voluntary:** Involved in several voluntary activities including youth mentoring and homeless night shelter **IT:** Software engineering, web development, completed A-level ICT, experienced in all Microsoft office applications and frequent user of the Internet.

Other: Represented my university nationally in the IBM Universities Business Challenge

# **Tosin Orekoya BSc CPFA**

References

Available on request